Finding Aid for Washtenaw County Historical Society records, 1827-2014
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Washtenaw County Historical Society records 1827-2014
Washtenaw County Historical Society.
1 oversize folders UBPl
17.5 linear feet (in 18 boxes)
86315 Bp.2 2; UBPl
Local historical society for Washtenaw County, Michigan Organizational records and collected historical materials.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The records were deposited by the Society (donor no. 945 ). Periodic additions have been received.
Periodic additions to the records are expected.
The record group is open to research.
On December 17, 1857, 19 citizens of Ann Arbor called for "a county convention for the purpose of forming a County Historical Association" to be composed of anyone from the townships who cared to attend. The meeting was held at the Court House for the purpose of organizing a Washtenaw Historical Society. John Geddes became the chair of a committee consisting of one representative from each township plus the city of Ann Arbor. The committee was appointed to draw up a constitution "to awaken an interest in the towns." The group met again on January 13, 1858 to adopt the constitution and elect officers. The Honorable Munnis Kinney of Webster Township was elected president. The object was "to collect and preserve the history of the first settlement and growth of Washtenaw County, and to publish the same from time to time as shall be deemed advisable." No records of meetings beyond 1862 have been found to date. It appears the organization continued and that artifacts and archival material continued to be collected but the Civil War may have been the reason for the suspension of meetings.
In April 1873, the state legislature passed a resolution calling for the collecting and preserving of historical information relating to Michigan which resulted in the formation of the Historical Society of Michigan. This probably led Gen. Edward Clark, President of the Ann Arbor Pioneer & Historical Society to call for a meeting on Aug. 19, 1873 to reactivate the county society. A constitution and by-laws were adopted that same day and we became 'The Pioneer Society of the County Washtenaw." Alpheus Felch, ex-governor of Mich., former Justice of the Peace, former U.S. Senator and a UM law professor was elected president. The object stated this time was "to cultivate social relations, collect and preserve biographical sketches, statistics and historical facts and reminiscences, and to preserve and transmit the same to future generations." Members had to be a resident of the county for at least 20 years and dues were 25 cents a year.
In 1876 the Society was incorporated under state law, dues were to be no less than 25 cents and no more than $3.00, members had to be "not less than 40 years of age, who had resided in the county 25 years." At a meeting in 1883, the Honorable E.P. Allen of Ypsilanti stated, "We are now living in the high noon of the last civilization the world will know until it is burned up, and I do not believe the progress of the fifty years to come will be equal to that of the past half century."
Meetings were held in various locations around the county--at first in alternate months, then quarterly and finally only annually and on special occasions such as the 4th of July. Meetings were an all day affair with a business meeting in the morning, lunch prepared by the local ladies, and then reports and, if time, reminiscences of members. It appears that no meetings were held after 1925.
In 1929, the third constitution was drawn up. A new constitution was necessary because the organizers discovered that the old charter had expired in 1906. By this time the pioneers were getting fewer and fewer. The age and residency requirements were dropped and the name was changed to Washtenaw Historical Society. It was felt that the word county limited the activities of the Society. The objects stated this time were "to foster interest in the history of the Washtenaw Area, and to assemble and preserve in permanent collections all materials relating to that history." In 1943, the dues were $1.00 or one could get a lifetime membership for $50. By 1947, the lifetime membership cost had dropped to $25. There were 24 lifetime members in 1950.
Upon expiration of that charter, the Society reincorporated in 1955. When that charter expired in 1985, we were reincorporated in perpetuity as a non-profit organization and the name was changed to Washtenaw County Historical Society.
Through all of that time the Society never had a home. The need for a permanent site was first expressed in 1874 by William Gregory of Saline. In 1930, Dr. Carl Guthe, president of the Society, stated that "the development and fostering of community memory is the function of the WHS" and "the Society is making definite plans for securing an adequate home for the county's memory." Over the years, many locations were mentioned and some discussed at length.
In 1942, Marie Louise Douglass, daughter of Dr. Silas H. Douglass, bequeathed her home at 502 E. Huron along with real estate owned on E. Washington to the Regents of the University of Michigan "being it expressly provided, however, that it be known as the Washtenaw Historical Museum" and "that the enterprise be conducted as a joint museum for the display of the property of the Washtenaw Historical Museum, under the supervision of the Regents of the University of Michigan, with such cooperation, between the groups as may be desirable to effectuate that purpose." The Society was not specifically mentioned but most interpreted the will to include the Society because many of her personal items were left to the Society. The Regents tentatively accepted the terms and the Society held a special meeting to discuss the proposal. It was felt that $150,000 would be needed. Due to the war, most funds were going to the war effort and the Society decided they could not obtain the needed money so they declined. The committee noted that there were a number of other suitable residences in Ann Arbor that might be purchased or donated with an endowment for upkeep.
In 1955, the Society launched a drive to purchase Cobblestone Farm. They needed to raise $40,000 but were unable to do so. Other sites mentioned were Kempf House (too small), Danforth House at 303 E. Ann (demolished), one of the empty store fronts on Main St. Tuomy House was explored in 1967 (and again in 1996 and yet again in 2005). The fire house was considered but rejected due to lack of parking (sure doesn't seem to be a problem for the Hands-On Museum).
In 1974, Dave Pollack offered to purchase four acres of land on Fleming Creek from Fred Matthaei, Jr. which would include the grist mill and land to build a museum. The Society decided it would be too expensive. The spot, Parker Mill, is now run by the County Parks Commission. One site that almost was successful was the Barton Dam Powerhouse. In 1977, the society signed a lease for the Powerhouse and three acres of land. One problem was the access which was off Barton Shore Drive, a private road in Barton Hills. The city agreed to build a new access road off Whitmore Lake Rd. on land that it would purchase. The access problem, the dampness issue, and the inability to raise the money, not to mention the fact that the city decided to reclaim it to generate electricity, resulted in the loss of yet another potential site. We did hold an exhibit at the powerhouse as a fund raiser. The final chapter in our search began in the late 1980s when the University decided to demolish a home at 1015 Wall St. for a parking lot. When Susan Wineberg heard about it, she wrote a letter to the university planner, Fred Mayer, explaining the significance of the house and asking if they would consider moving it. The original lot on Wall Street was sold to Thomas Peatt by Anson Brown's widow and subsequently sold to Dan Kellogg and Ethan Warden. The rear section of the house was built in 1835 by Dorr, Dwight and Dan Kellogg. The front section was added in 1839 when Charles and his wife came from New York State.
The university offered the house to the city which accepted, then decided six months later that they had no use for it. At that time, Thelma Graves, a board member, suggested to the society president, Karen O'Neal, that the Society try to acquire the house from the University. Through Karen O'Neal's determination, the support of the university, the city's agreement to lease the land and in spite of setbacks, including a determination by the DNR that the soil was contaminated by the gas station previously on the site, the project became a reality. On Sunday, June 10, 1990, the Society's first home, the Museum on Main Street, rolled across the Broadway bridge and was set on cribbing, 133 years after John Geddes called for the formation of a society.
[This text was edited from the Washtenaw County Historical Society web-site]
The Washtenaw County Historical Society records include collected historical documents and photographs relating to the people, events, and history of the county, its cities and townships. There are also administrative records of the organization, including minutes of meetings, subjects relating to Society programs and projects, and financial miscellanea.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.: Township); Bank of Washtenaw.; Banks and banking--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Birmingham (Mich.); Bridgewater (Mich.: Township); Dexter (Mich.: Township); Freedom (Mich.: Township); Frontier and pioneer life--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Grand Army of the Republic. Welch Post No. 137 (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Ladies Decoration Society (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Lima (Mich.: Township); Lodi (Mich.: Township); Lyndon (Mich.: Township); McAndrew, Helen Walker, 1826-1906.; McCollum, Walter.; Manchester (Mich.: Township); Northfield (Mich.: Township); Pittsfield (Mich.: Township); Railroads--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Salem (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township); Saline (Mich.: Township); Scio (Mich.: Township); Sharon (Washtenaw County, Mich.); Superior (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township); Sylvan (Washtenaw County, Mich.: Township); United States. Army. Michigan Infantry Regiment, 4th (1861-1864). Company D.; United States. Army. Michigan Artillery Regiment, 6th (1863-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan--History.; Wagner Company (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Washtenaw County Historical Society.; World's Columbian Exposition (1893: Chicago, Ill.); York (Mich.: Township); Ypsilanti (Mich.); Ypsilanti (Mich.: Township)
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Adams, Charles Kendall, 1835-1902.; Ann Arbor City Mills.; Ann Arbor High School (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.); Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Buildings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Churches.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Ann Arbor (Mich.)--Post offices.; Buildings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Buildings--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Burnett, Arthur W.; Churches--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Demmon, Isaac Newton, 1842-1920.; Dunster, Edward Swift, 1834-1888.; Dwellings--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Dwellings--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Christian Eberbach House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Frieze, Henry S. (Henry Simmons), 1817-1889.; Haven, E. O. (Erastus Otis), 1820-1881.; Hempl, George, 1859-1921.; Interiors.; Jones, Charles Nelson, 1848-1913.; Laboratories.; Laborers.; Loomis House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); MacLean, Donald, 1839-1903.; Manchester (Mich.); Mills.; Morgan House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Muehlig House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Newspaper carriers.; Offices.; Palmer, Alice Freeman, 1855-1902.; Pond, Elihu Bartlit, 1826-1898.; Post offices--Michigan--Ann Arbor.; Reighard House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Saline (Mich.); Sault Sainte Marie (Mich.); Tyler, Moses Coit, 1835-1900.; United States. Army. Michigan Artillery Regiment, 6th (1863-1865); United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865.; University of Michigan--Buildings.; University of Michigan--Campus.; Van Hoosen, Bertha, 1863-1952; Washtenaw County (Mich.); Washtenaw County (Mich.)--Buildings.; Washtenaw County (Mich.)--Dwellings.; Winchell House (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Women.; Ypsilanti (Mich.)
Subjects - Sound Recordings:
Washtenaw County Historical Society.; Artists--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Women artists--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Washtenaw County (Mich.)
Contributors:
Allen, John, 1796-1851.; Bronson, Titus, 1788-1853.; Chapin, Lucy E., 1834-1910.; Chicago, Burlington & Quincy Railroad Company.; Forest Hill Cemetery (Ann Arbor, Mich.); Howell, Seymour, 1841-1909.; Lyon, Lucius, 1800-1851.; Maynard, William Sumner, 1802-1866.; Gilbert, Edwin H.
Contributors: Sound Recordings
Taylor, Howell, Mrs.
Genre Terms:
Albums.; Ambrotypes.; Daguerreotypes.; Paintings.; Slides.; Photographs.; Stereographs.; Tintypes.; Sound recordings.
- Collected historical materials
  - Land grant and letter 1948 concerning Archer Crane (Box 1)
    (1)
  - Bill 1846 amending act which incorporated the village of Ann Arbor (Box 1)
    (2)
  - History 1950 of the Washtenaw Historical Society written by F. Clever Bald (Box 1)
    (3)
  - Ann Arbor printed materials (Box 1)
    (4)
  - Ypsilanti printed materials (include memorial book about Helen W. McAndrew) (Box 1)
    (5)
  - History of the Ladies Decoration Society undated (Box 1)
    (6)
  - School papers of Frances J. Allen undated (Box 1)
    (7)
  - Petition 1832 signed by supporters of the Jackson administration (Box 1)
    (8)
  - Lucy Chapin materials
    (see also separate Lucy Chapin collection)
    - Miscellaneous collected autographs (Box 1)
      (9)
    - Collected clippings re the University of Michigan (Box 1)
      (10)
    - Collected clippings re Washtenaw County (Box 1)
      (11)
    - Collected clippings re Ann Arbor (Box 1)
      (12)
  - Miscellaneous clippings, programs and correspondence (Box 1)
    (13)
  - Grand Army of the Republic miscellanea (Box 1)
    (17; no folders 14-16)
  - Semi-Centennial celebration of Washtenaw County miscellanea 1874 (Box 1)
    (18)
  - Columbian Exposition (Box 1)
    (19)
  - E. Clark materials (papers concerning the Territorial Road in Ann Arbor and the first duel in Ann Arbor (Box 1)
    (20)
  - Inventories 1867, 1870-1872 of a dry goods store (Box 1)
    (21)
  - Poems and plays (Box 1)
    (22)
  - William Maynard mortgage (Box 1)
    (22a)
  - Message of the governor of New York 1824 (Box 1)
    (23)
  - 6th Michigan Heavy Artillery records (papers of Seymour Howell) 1863-1866
    (These records, in addition to other Seymour personal papers, have been microfilmed. The original materials, folders 24-44, are closed to research)
    - Invoices of ordnance and ordnance stores
      - 1863-1864 (Box 2)
        (24)
      - January-March 1865 (Box 2)
        (25)
      - April-September 1865 (Box 2)
        (26)
    - Receipts for ordnance stores (Box 2)
      (27)
    - Abstracts 1865 of receipts (Box 2)
      (28)
    - Receipts 1864-1865 of clothes, and camp and garrison equipment (Box 2)
      (29)
    - Requisitions 1864-1865 for ordnance stores (Box 2)
      (30)
    - Reports 1864 on the returns of clothing, camp and garrison equipage (Box 2)
      (31)
    - Report 1864-1865 of quarterly return of ordnance and ordnance stores (Box 2)
      (32)
    - Special field orders 1864-1865 (Box 2)
      (33)
    - General orders 1863-1865 of the War Dept. (Box 2)
      (34)
    - Printed communications 1863-1864 of the Ordnance Office (Box 2)
      (35)
    - Official communications 1864-1866 of the Ordnance Office (Box 2)
      (36)
    - Papers 1863-1865 include official correspondence (Box 2)
      (37)
    - Correspondence 1864-1866 of Capt. Seymour Howell (Box 2)
      (38)
    - List 1865 of articles received by Seymour Howell at Fort Gaines, Ala. (Box 2)
      (39)
    - Miscellaneous lists (Box 2)
      (40)
    - Inventory 1865 of ordnance stores (Box 2)
      (41)
    - Proceedings 1865 of board of survey at Fort Gaines, Ala. (Box 2)
      (42)
    - Abstracts 1863-1865 of expenditures at Fort Gaines, Ala. (Box 2)
      (43)
    - Miscellaneous 1860s include Civil War blank forms (Box 2)
      (44)
  - Edwin H. Gilbert (Co. D, 4th Michigan Infantry) papers 1862-1865, undated (Box 11)
    (These records, have been microfilmed. The original materials, folders 45-49, are closed to research)
  - Arithmetic books 1822 of Amelia Roosa (Box 12)
    (53; no folders 50-51)
  - Nineteenth century bank notes (Box 12)
    (54)
  - Auction notice 1827 of lots in Ypsilanti (Box 12)
    (55)
  - Lease of Detroit, Hillsdale and Southwestern Railroad to Lake Shore and Michigan Southern Railroad September 5, 1881 (Box 12)
    (56)
  - William Wagner papers
    - Receipts 1849-1902 also miscellaneous accounts (Box 12)
      (57)
    - Correspondence 1869, 1871 (Box 12)
      (58)
  - Scrapbook of late nineteenth century greeting cards (Box 12)
    (60; no folder 59)
  - Article by William J. Armstrong entitled, "The Great Trail that Became the Chicago Road" (Box 12)
    (61)
  - Washtenaw Impressions (papers used in) (Box 12)
    (62)
  - Geneva Smithe research materials (intended for use in history of Washtenaw County (Box 12)
    (64)
  - County and township materials
    - Ann Arbor Township (Box 12)
      (65)
    - Bridgewater Township (Box 12)
      (66)
    - Dexter Township (Box 12)
      (67)
    - Freedom Township (Box 12)
      (68)
    - Lima Township (Box 12)
      (69)
    - Lodi Township (Box 12)
      (70)
    - Lyndon Township (Box 12)
      (71)
    - Manchester Township (Box 12)
      (72)
    - Northfield Township (Box 12)
      (73)
    - Pittsfield Township (Box 12)
      (74)
    - Salem Township (Box 12)
      (75)
    - Saline Township (Box 12)
      (76)
    - Scio Township (Box 12)
      (77)
    - Sharon Township (Box 12)
      (78)
    - Superior Township (Box 12)
      (79)
    - Sylvan Township (Box 12)
      (80)
    - York Township (Box 12)
      (81)
    - Ypsilanti Township (Box 12)
      (82)
    - Notebooks re. county pioneers 1916-1926 (Box 12)
      (83)
    - Obituaries of county residents (Box 12)
      (84)
    - Obituaries of county residents 1876-1886 (Box 12)
      (85)
    - Clippings, mainly obituaries, of county residents 1870s-1880s (Box 13)
      (86)
    - Obituaries of county residents 1938-1952 (mainly clippings) (Box 13)
      (87)
  - Miscellanea (Box 13)
    (88)
  - Jewell addition to Ann Arbor (paper about) 1871 (Box 13)
    (89)
  - Volume of poetry presented to Lucy Ann Kingsley 1820s-1830s (Box 13)
  - Scrapbook of Theresa Graves (largely concerning Ypsilanti, Michigan, history and citizens) (Box 13)
- Organizational Records
  - 1873-1979
    - Minutes and membership book 1873-1929 of the Washtenaw County Pioneer Society (Box 3)
      (90)
    - Minutes and reports undated, 1929-1978, 17 folders (Box 3)
      (91-107)
    - Activities file 1957-1973 (Box 3)
      (108)
    - Officers file 1968-1979 (Box 3)
      (109)
    - Business correspondence
      - 1913-1953 (Box 3)
        (110)
      - 1968-1973 (Box 3)
        (111)
    - Constitution, bylaws, rules 1873-1966 (Box 3)
      (112)
    - Scrapbook 1877-1951 (Box 3)
      (113)
  - 1978-2014
    - Burns Park cabin-names on logs report (includes photographs) 1991 (Box 14)
    - Bylaws, constitution, and collections policy statement (Box 14)
    - Development study 1978 (Box 14)
    - Financial records 1978-1985 (Box 14)
    - IRS exempt status 1990 (Box 14)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors 1978-1988, 1992-2014, 13 folders (Box 14)
    - Minutes of the Board of Directors 1980-2002 (Box 4)
      (include files maintained by Alice Ziegler)
    - Minutes and annual and regular meetings 1978-1984 (Box 9)
    - Museum fund drive 1976-1979 (Box 9)
    - Photographs, 3 folders (Box 9)
    - Washtenaw Genealogical Society 1974-1978, 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Woodruff-Seymour Woodruff Bible record (Box 9)
    - 125th birthday celebration 1982 (Box 9)
    - Notebook circa 1986 containing copies of information from the minutes relating especially to gifts, collections, storage places, etc., 1873-1980 (Box 9)
    - President's files (Galen Wilson; 1985-87) 1984-1988, 22 folders
      - Agendas 1984-1987 (Box 9)
      - Aliens & Scoundrels (sesquicentennial comedy) 1986-1987, 8 folders (Box 9)
      - Articles of incorporation, by-laws, WCHS legal status (Box 9)
      - Book Committee (Ruth Bordin history) 1984-1987 (Box 9)
      - Calendar: Bill Shurliff calendar 1986 (Box 9)
      - Collections 1985-1987 (Box 9)
      - Correspondence 1983-1987 (Box 9)
      - Lists: membership, officers, committees (Box 9)
      - Long-Range Planning Committee 1985-1986 (Box 9)
      - Meetings 1983-1988 (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous (include photographs) (Box 9)
      - Reports 1983-1987 (Box 9)
      - Sesquicentennial Advisory Committee 1985-1987 (Box 9)
      - Telephone dispute (Box 9)
      - Treasurer's reports 1984-1987 (Box 9)
    - Miscellaneous topical files 1990s (Box 10)
    - Sound cassettes of meeting programs (Box 10)
  - Various WCHS officers, various dates
    (unprocessed)
    - Secretary-treasurer (Geneva Smithe) files (Box 15)
    - Secretary (Ethelyn S. Morton) files (Box 15)
    - Secretary-treasurer (Katherine Groomes) files (Box 15)
    - Secretary-treasurer (Katherine Groomes) files (Box 16)
    - Recording secretary and newsletter editor (Alice Ziegler) topical files (Box 16)
    - Recording secretary (Alice Ziegler) notes and notebooks on board meetings (Box 17)
    - Miscellaneous and unprocessed (Box 18)
- Photographs
  - Ann Arbor
    - Businesses: include women in bean factory (Box 5)
    - Civil War announcement: President Tappan addressing the community 1861 (Box 5)
    - High School (Box 5)
    - Houses and churches (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous: include Broadway Bridge train-wreck (Box 5)
    - Veterans group (Folder 1)
      (located in UBPl)
    - Views-countryside, 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Views-street and town (Box 5)
      (see also oversized, UBPl)
  - Manchester (Box 5)
  - Saline (Box 5)
  - Sault Ste. Marie (Box 5)
  - Ypsilanti
    - General (Box 5)
    - Roosevelt High School (Box 5)
  - Individuals, 3 folders
    - Adams, Charles Kendall (Box 5)
    - Andrews, Lucy C (Box 5)
    - Armendt, W.B. (Box 5)
    - Armstrong, George W. and Martha J. (Box 5)
    - Ayers, Howard (Box 5)
    - Barrett, Kate (Box 5)
    - Bickford, Elizabeth E. (Box 5)
    - Bislif, Harriet H. (Box 5)
    - Breakey, W.F. (Box 5)
    - Brown, Dan B. (Box 5)
    - Burnett, Arthur William (Box 5)
    - Chamberlain, Winthrop B. (Box 5)
    - Chapin, Angie C. (Box 5)
    - Collier, Hattie Marie (Box 5)
    - Cowles, Dr. and Mrs. (Box 5)
    - Crocker, ? (Box 5)
    - Demmon, Isaac Newton (Box 5)
    - Dodd, Charles W. (Box 5)
    - Draper, H. (Box 5)
    - Dunster, (Dr.) (Box 5)
    - Eyer, Jane (Box 5)
    - Farrand, Mary Porter (Box 5)
    - Farrand, Porter Drew (2) (Box 5)
    - Frieze, Henry Simmons (Box 5)
    - Harris, Linda Enos (Box 5)
    - Haven, Eratus O. (Box 5)
    - Hemple, George (GH in office) (Box 5)
    - Hewitt, Walter B. (Box 5)
    - Hills, Laura (2) (Box 5)
    - Howe, Seth (Box 5)
    - Howland, Amy White (Box 5)
    - Hubbard (Grandmother) (Box 5)
    - Hubbard, T.H. (Box 5)
    - Jones, Chalres Nelson (Box 5)
    - Jones, Elisha (Box 5)
    - Kellogg, C.A. (Box 5)
    - Knowlton, Elizabeth Chase Bailey (Box 5)
    - de League, Mathilde (Box 5)
    - Lund, Almy Richmond (Box 5)
    - Lyon, Florence May (Box 5)
    - Mahon, Henry L. (Box 5)
    - Mark, Edward Laurens (Box 5)
    - Maroin, C.M. (Box 5)
    - Marston, Mary (Box 5)
    - Martin, Julia (Box 5)
    - McCollum, Walter (Box 5)
    - McLean, Donald (Box 5)
    - Mobbs, Albertine and Josephine (Box 5)
    - Okemos (Box 5)
    - Palmer, Alice Freeman (Box 5)
    - Parshall, James J. (Box 5)
    - Payne, Louise (Box 5)
    - Pierce, Newton B. (Box 5)
    - Pond, Elihu (Box 5)
    - Reighard, John E. (Box 5)